<appendix xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
          xmlns:xi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude'
          xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
          version="5.2">
<info>
<title>Unified NineML change log</title>
</info>

<para>This appendix is a unified change log for all of the NineML
components in this repository. It’s never formatted directly, it’s
distributed into the different component repositories during the
build. Having the source in a single place is an attempt to simplify
managing the change log. The log is used automatically in the release
notes for each component.</para>

<para>The unified log starts at version 3.0.0m. Previous history is in
the individual component <filename>changelogs.xml</filename> files.</para>

<revhistory>
<revision xml:id="v311">
<revnumber>3.1.1</revnumber>
<date>2023-08-02</date>
<revdescription>
<para audience="coffeesacks">Fixed a bug in the construction of the graph that
an <classname>XPathAxe</classname> gets to inspect. Nodes were inadvertantly being
processed many (many!) times in ambiguous forests making the construction very slow.</para>
<para audience="coffeegrinder"/>
<para audience="coffeefilter"/>
<para audience="coffeepot"/>
</revdescription>
</revision>
<revision xml:id="v310">
<revnumber>3.1.0</revnumber>
<date>2023-08-01</date>
<revdescription>
<itemizedlist audience="coffeegrinder">
<listitem>
<para>Added support for marking horizontal ambiguities with processing
instructions.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<itemizedlist audience="coffeefilter">
<listitem>
<para>Added support for specifying an alternate start symbol for parsing.
This is not conformant behavior, but is useful for converted grammars that may
have otherwise unreachable states.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Added more checks for grammars provided in XML form. Removed some unused rules
from the internal pragmas grammar.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Improved the way ambiguity is detected and reported.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<itemizedlist audience="coffeesacks">
<listitem>
<para>Refactored the way parser options are constructed. There’s now a separate
options object for each grammar and parser.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Cleaned up the names of the parser options that can be passed in the XPath
options map.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Fixed a bug where the default Axe failed to report ambiguous choices if there
were no selectors (XPath expressions or functions) provided at all.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<itemizedlist audience="coffeepot">
<listitem>
<para>Hygiene issues with the grammar are now logged at the debug level.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Added a <option>--start-symbol</option> option to select an alternate start symbol.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</revdescription>
</revision>

<revision xml:id="v300">
<revnumber>3.0.0</revnumber>
<date>2023-07-29</date>
<revdescription>
<itemizedlist audience="coffeegrinder">
<listitem>
<para>Many improvements and bug fixes in the GLL parser. It is now often (slightly)
faster than the Earley parser and should be just as reliable.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Refactored how trees are returned from the forest. In principle, it is possible
to retrieve all of the trees.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>When prefix parsing is enabled, it is now possible to continue the parse with
a different parser.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Refactored tests to use JUnit 5 exclusively, many new and improved tests.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Refactored and improved how and where terminals can be matched with regular
expressions. Regular expression matches work with both parsers.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Many improvements to the <filename>forest2dot.xsl</filename> stylesheet that
produces forest diagrams.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Added an option to analyze the grammar for ambiguity
with Anders Møller’s
<link xlink:href="https://www.brics.dk/grammar/">ambiguity analyzer</link>.
(Note that the analyzer jar file is included in the repository, but
it isn’t bundled with CoffeeGrinder, you need to add it to your class
path. It is bundled with CoffeePot.)</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Parser attributes (used internally to track marks and other
features) have been renamed so that they’re all URIs. Added an
attribute to track nonterminal priority. (To guide selection in
ambiguous forests.)
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Added an option to normalize line endings on input.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Added an option to mark ambiguities. When enabled, this option
identifies places in the tree where an ambiguous choice was made.
(It currently only works for “vertical” ambiguities between nonterminals.)
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<itemizedlist audience="coffeefilter">
<listitem>
<para>All of the NineML core components have been updated to version 3.0.0; 
CoffeeFilter incorporates the changes in
<link xlink:href="https://coffeegrinder.nineml.org/changelog.html#v300">CoffeeGrinder</link>
3.0.0.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Added support for the <link xlink:href="https://invisiblexml.org/pr/193/index.html">renaming
proposal</link> provided that the grammar identifies itself as version 1.1 (or 1.1-nineml).
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Refactored how pragmas are processed; removed the unused “token” pragma.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Removed the “rewrite” pragma; it can be replaced with standard features:
deletion and insertion. Removed the default priority pragma because it didn’t actually seem
useful.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Removed the notion of compiled grammars and the cache of compiled grammars.
</para></listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Added an option to omit headers when generating CSV output.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Added support for the “mark ambiguities” option. When enabled
<code>n:ambiguous="true"</code> attributes are added to the XML
trees.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<itemizedlist audience="coffeesacks">
<listitem>
<para>All of the NineML core components have been updated to version 3.0.0; 
CoffeeSacks incorporates the changes in
<link xlink:href="https://coffeegrinder.nineml.org/changelog.html#v300">CoffeeGrinder</link>
and
<link xlink:href="https://coffeefilter.nineml.org/changelog.html#v300">CoffeeFilter</link>
3.0.0.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>The API for resolving ambiguities has been completely refactored to align with 
CoffeeGrinder.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<itemizedlist audience="coffeepot">
<listitem>
<para>All of the NineML core components have been updated to version 3.0.0; 
CoffeePot incorporates the changes in
<link xlink:href="https://coffeegrinder.nineml.org/changelog.html#v300">CoffeeGrinder</link>,
<link xlink:href="https://coffeefilter.nineml.org/changelog.html#v300">CoffeeFilter</link>,
and
<link xlink:href="https://coffeesacks.nineml.org/changelog.html#v300">CoffeeSacks</link>,
3.0.0.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Many new command line options and configuration properties have been
added; a few have been renamed or removed.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>CoffeePot will now work with either Saxon 11 or Saxon 12.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Undefined symbols are no longer allowed, even when not in pedantic mode.
Undefined symbols are almost always an error and lead to very confusing error messages.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Added an option to analyze the grammar for ambiguity
with Anders Møller’s <link
xlink:href="https://www.brics.dk/grammar/">ambiguity analyzer</link>.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Support for compiled grammars and grammar compilation has been removed.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Fixed a number of small serialization bugs.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</revdescription>
</revision>
</revhistory>

</appendix>
