<appendix xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
          xmlns:xi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude'
          xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
          version="5.2">
<info>
<title>Unified NineML change log</title>
</info>

<para>This appendix is a unified change log for all of the NineML
components in this repository. It’s never formatted directly, it’s
distributed into the different component repositories during the
build. Having the source in a single place is an attempt to simplify
managing the change log. The log is used automatically in the release
notes for each component.</para>

<para>The unified log starts at version 3.0.0m. Previous history is in
the individual component <filename>changelogs.xml</filename> files.</para>

<revhistory>
<revision>
<revnumber>3.0.0m</revnumber>
<date>2023-07-28</date>
<revdescription>
<para>This is a beta release for version 3.0.0.</para>

<itemizedlist audience="coffeegrinder">
<listitem>
<para>Fixed a bug where the GLL parser would fail to correctly find the
parser attributes associated with a “left hand side”.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Fixed a bug in the ambiguity analyzer where
it didn’t support Unicode character class groupings (LC, L, M, N, P, S, Z, C).
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Added an option to normalize line endings.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Added an option to mark ambiguities. When enabled, this option
identifies places in the tree where an ambiguous choice was made.
(This only works for vertical ambiguities on nonterminals that aren’t
suppressed.)
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para audience="coffeefilter">Added support for the “mark ambiguities” option. When
enabled <code>n:ambiguous="true"</code> attributes are added to the XML trees.</para>

<para audience="coffeesacks"/> <!-- no changes -->

<itemizedlist audience="coffeepot">
<listitem>
<para>Fixed a serialization bug where a newline was sometimes
missing before a closing tag when pretty printing was enabled.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Fixed a serialization bug where the “trailing newline on
output” option was ignored.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Added a <option>--normalize</option> option
and a <property>normalize-line-endings</property> property
to enable normalizing line endings on the input.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Added a <option>--mark-ambiguities</option>
option and a <property>mark-ambiguities</property> property to support
marking the location of ambiguities in the XML trees.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Added a <option>--provenance</option>
option and a <property>provenance</property> property to support
writing provenance (program version, input, grammar details) as
a comment at the top of XML outputs.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Moved the ambiguity report output from
“standard output” to “standard error” so that command line redirection
once again only includes the XML. Added a <option>--debug</option>
option.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</revdescription>
</revision>
</revhistory>

</appendix>
