<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude'
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xml:id="choose-alternative_cs"
         version="5.2">
<title>Choosing among alternatives</title>

<note><para>This API has been completely rewritten for version 3.0.0.</para>
</note>

<para>Where it’s practical to write a grammar that is unambiguous,
that’s best. But it isn’t always practical. Sometimes it’s difficult,
and sometimes it’s impossible. If the data is actually ambiguous, you
may have to reflect that in your grammar.</para>

<para>Invisible XML doesn’t consider ambiguity an error, but it also
doesn’t provide any mechanism for controlling it. All parses are
considered equal and the processor’s only obligation is to provide one
of them.</para>

<para>That may not suit your needs. CoffeeSacks provides a way to
examine the alternatives and select one. You can supply a
<code>choose-alternative</code> function in the parser options. This
must take two arguments, an element and a map, and return a map.
</para>

<para>The function receives a context element that identifies its
location in the parse forest and a map that describes the current
state of the parse:</para>

<informaltable>
<tgroup cols="2">
<thead>
<row>
<entry>Property</entry>
<entry>Value</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
  <entry><code>input</code></entry>
  <entry>The input string</entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry><code>available-choices</code></entry>
  <entry>A list of available choices</entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry><code>other-choices</code></entry>
  <entry>A list of other choices</entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry><replaceable>user-defined</replaceable></entry>
  <entry>User defined properties</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>

<para>The function must return a map that contains a <code>selection</code> property that
identifies the choice made. It may also return an <code>ambiguous-choice</code> property to
indicate that an abitrary, ambiguous choice was made.</para>

<para>Any other properties returned in the map will be passed back on the next call.
This allows the selection function to maintain state between invocations.</para>

<para>The function must return one of the choices passed to it. There will always be
at least one item in the <code>choices</code> list. The difference between the available
choices and the “other” choices is only relevant when the grammar contains a loop. If the
grammar loops, the previously selected choices will be in <code>other-choices</code>.
Only choose from that list if you have some other way to avoid looping infinitely.</para>

<para>This function always selects the first alternative:</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<xsl:function name="f:first" as="map(*)">
  <xsl:param name="context" as="element()"/>
  <xsl:param name="options" as="map(*)"/>

  <xsl:sequence select="map { 'selection': $options?available-choices[1] }"/>
</xsl:function>]]></programlisting>

<para>You could pass it in parse options like this:</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<xsl:variable name="parser"
              select="cs:make-parser($grammar,
                      map{'choose-alternative: f:first#2})"/>]]></programlisting>

<para>Of course, unconditionally choosing the first option isn’t very
interesting. To explore further, consider this simple, ambiguous
grammar:</para>

<programlisting language="ixml">   number-list = (number, -#a)+, number? .
        number = hex | decimal .
           hex = hex-digit+ .
       decimal = decimal-digit+ .
    -hex-digit = ["0"-"9" | "a"-"f" | "A"-"F" ] .
-decimal-digit = ["0"-"9" ] .</programlisting>

<para>If we parse the following input,</para>

<programlisting><xi:include href="numbers.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>

<para>We might get this result:</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<number-list xmlns:ixml="http://invisiblexml.org/NS" ixml:state="ambiguous">
  <hex>bad</hex>
  <hex>cafe</hex>
  <hex>42</hex>
</number-list>]]></programlisting>

<para>Of course, we might equally get this result:</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<number-list xmlns:ixml="http://invisiblexml.org/NS" ixml:state="ambiguous">
  <hex>bad</hex>
  <hex>cafe</hex>
  <decimal>42</decimal>
</number-list>]]></programlisting>

<para>The ambiguity here is between “decimal” and “hexidecimal”.
Here’s a function that will always select the decimal alternative:
</para>

<programlisting language="xml"
><xi:include href="decimal.xsl"
             fragid="text(line=20,30;md5=1232dea15d3569dd402570056285290c)" parse="text"
/></programlisting>

<para>In order to understand how this works, we need to look at what’s
passed to the function. The function get’s a context element that is
an XML description of the current state of the parse, and a map. For
our example, the map would look something like this:</para>

<programlisting>map {
  "input":"bad
cafe
42",
  "available-choices": ("C3464","C3465"),
  "other-choices":()
}</programlisting>

<para>And the context element like this:</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<symbol name="number" id="N3694" mark="^" start="10" length="2">
   <parent ref="N3695">$4_number-option</parent>
   <children id="C3464" priority="0">
      <symbol name="hex" ref="N3692" start="10" length="2"/>
   </children>
   <children id="C3465" priority="0">
      <symbol name="decimal" ref="N3693" start="10" length="2"/>
   </children>
</symbol>]]></programlisting>

<para>This is a choice being made for the symbol “number”. There are
two choices, identified by “children”. In this example, each of the
alternatives is a single symbol, but the context can be more complex.
For each symbol, we also get the range of characters that it covers in
the input. For each choice, it’s computed priority. The context is
always the specific choice that’s being made, but the whole forest is
available. Each of the “N” references can be used to find the
corresponding nodes for those symbols.</para>

<para>Which aspects of the context (if any) are relevant is going to
depend on your grammar and the input.</para>

<section xml:id="grammar-details">
<title>Grammar details</title>

<para>Invisible XML is an example of an
<link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Extended_Backus%E2%80%93Naur_form">extended
Backus-Naur form</link> (EBNF) grammar. The underlying parsing technlogies, either Earley or GLL, operate
on simple <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Backus%E2%80%93Naur_form">Backus-Naur
form</link> (BNF) grammars. What that means in practice is that the first thing
<link xlink:href="https://coffeegrinder.nineml.org">CoffeeGrinder</link> does to your Invisible
XML grammar is
<link xlink:href="https://github.com/invisibleXML/ixml/blob/master/misc/ebnf-to-bnf.md">convert it</link>
into a plain BNF. That process introduces new nonterminals.</para>

<para>Mostly this is a behind-the-scenes transformation that isn’t
relevant to the user, but it’s inescapable when describing ambiguity.
Ultimately, the ambiguity is in the BNF and that’s the only grammar
that the parser can describe.</para>

<para>The oddly named nonterminals seen above come from the fact that
our iXML grammar has been transformed into this BNF:</para>

<programlisting>                   $$ ::= number-list
          number-list ::= $1_number-plus, $4_number-optionⁿ
               number ::= hex
               number ::= decimal
                  hex ::= $2_hex-digit-plus
              decimal ::= $3_decimal-digit-plus
            hex-digit ::= ['0'-'9'; 'a'-'f'; 'A'-'F']
        decimal-digit ::= ['0'-'9']
       $1_number-plus ::= number, #A
       $1_number-plus ::= number, #A, $1_number-plus
    $2_hex-digit-plus ::= hex-digit
    $2_hex-digit-plus ::= hex-digit, $2_hex-digit-plus
$3_decimal-digit-plus ::= decimal-digit
$3_decimal-digit-plus ::= decimal-digit, $3_decimal-digit-plus
    $4_number-optionⁿ ::= ε
    $4_number-optionⁿ ::= number</programlisting>

<para>This grammar is simpler in the sense that the rules for matching
tokens in the input are simpler. There are no repetitions,
alternatives, or other features on the “right hand side” of each production.</para>

<para>It appears more complicated partly because there are more
productions and there can be multiple productions for any given
nonterminal. It also appears more complicated because it’s impossible
to generate semantically meaningful names for the new nonterminals introduced.</para>

</section>
</chapter>
