<appendix xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
          xmlns:xi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude'
          xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
          xml:id="changelog"
          version="5.2">
<info>
<?db filename='../changelog.html'?>
<title>Unified change log</title>
</info>

<para>This appendix is a unified change log for all of the NineML
components in this repository.</para>

<!--
N.B.: the log is used automatically in the release notes for each component.
-->

<revhistory role="changelog">
<revision xml:id="v321">
<revnumber>3.2.1</revnumber>
<date>2023-08-06</date>
<revdescription>
<para audience="coffeegrinder">Fixes
<link xlink:href="https://github.com/nineml/nineml/issues/17">a bug</link> in
prefix parsing.</para>
<para audience="coffeefilter"/>
<para audience="coffeesacks"/>
<para audience="coffeepot"/>
</revdescription>
</revision>
<revision xml:id="v320">
<revnumber>3.2.0</revnumber>
<date>2023-08-04</date>
<revdescription>
<para audience="coffeegrinder">Reworked how the <classname>Arborist</classname> classes track
and provide descriptions of how ambiguity was resolved.</para>
<para audience="coffeefilter"/>
<itemizedlist audience="coffeesacks">
<listitem>
<para>Fixed a bug in the construction of the graph that
an <classname>XPathAxe</classname> gets to inspect. Nodes were inadvertantly being
processed many (many!) times in ambiguous forests making the construction very slow.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Changed the <classname>XmlForest</classname> used for resolving ambiguities in the
<classname>XPathAxe</classname> so that it includes nodes for intermediate states.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<itemizedlist audience="coffeepot">
<listitem>
<para>The <option>--describe-ambiguity</option> option was broken in
the previous 3.x releases. It was a fair bit of effort to restore it. The descriptions
have changed a bit and the <literal>api-xml</literal> option has been removed (the “API” flavor
is returned by the <literal>xml</literal> option).
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Added an <option>--axe</option> option and support for a <literal>random</literal> axe.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Added a <option>--trim</option> option to trim leading and trailing whitespace off
the input. (This can be handy if you have input in a file, your editor automatically adds
a newline at the end of the file, and your grammar doesn’t support trailing whitespace.)
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</revdescription>
</revision>
<revision xml:id="v310">
<revnumber>3.1.0</revnumber>
<date>2023-08-01</date>
<revdescription>
<itemizedlist audience="coffeegrinder">
<listitem>
<para>Added support for marking horizontal ambiguities with processing
instructions.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<itemizedlist audience="coffeefilter">
<listitem>
<para>Added support for specifying an alternate start symbol for parsing.
This is not conformant behavior, but is useful for converted grammars that may
have otherwise unreachable states.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Added more checks for grammars provided in XML form. Removed some unused rules
from the internal pragmas grammar.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Improved the way ambiguity is detected and reported.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<itemizedlist audience="coffeesacks">
<listitem>
<para>Refactored the way parser options are constructed. There’s now a separate
options object for each grammar and parser.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Cleaned up the names of the parser options that can be passed in the XPath
options map.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Fixed a bug where the default Axe failed to report ambiguous choices if there
were no selectors (XPath expressions or functions) provided at all.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<itemizedlist audience="coffeepot">
<listitem>
<para>Hygiene issues with the grammar are now logged at the debug level.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Added a <option>--start-symbol</option> option to select an alternate start symbol.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</revdescription>
</revision>

<revision xml:id="v300">
<revnumber>3.0.0</revnumber>
<date>2023-07-29</date>
<revdescription>
<itemizedlist audience="coffeegrinder">
<listitem>
<para>Many improvements and bug fixes in the GLL parser. It is now often (slightly)
faster than the Earley parser and should be just as reliable.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Refactored how trees are returned from the forest. In principle, it is possible
to retrieve all of the trees.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>When prefix parsing is enabled, it is now possible to continue the parse with
a different parser.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Refactored tests to use JUnit 5 exclusively, many new and improved tests.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Refactored and improved how and where terminals can be matched with regular
expressions. Regular expression matches work with both parsers.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Many improvements to the <filename>forest2dot.xsl</filename> stylesheet that
produces forest diagrams.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Added an option to analyze the grammar for ambiguity
with Anders Møller’s
<link xlink:href="https://www.brics.dk/grammar/">ambiguity analyzer</link>.
(Note that the analyzer jar file is included in the repository, but
it isn’t bundled with CoffeeGrinder, you need to add it to your class
path. It is bundled with CoffeePot.)</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Parser attributes (used internally to track marks and other
features) have been renamed so that they’re all URIs. Added an
attribute to track nonterminal priority. (To guide selection in
ambiguous forests.)
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Added an option to normalize line endings on input.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Added an option to mark ambiguities. When enabled, this option
identifies places in the tree where an ambiguous choice was made.
(It currently only works for “vertical” ambiguities between nonterminals.)
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<itemizedlist audience="coffeefilter">
<listitem>
<para>All of the NineML core components have been updated to version 3.0.0; 
CoffeeFilter incorporates the changes in
<link xlink:href="https://coffeegrinder.nineml.org/changelog.html#v300">CoffeeGrinder</link>
3.0.0.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Added support for the <link xlink:href="https://invisiblexml.org/pr/193/index.html">renaming
proposal</link> provided that the grammar identifies itself as version 1.1 (or 1.1-nineml).
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Refactored how pragmas are processed; removed the unused “token” pragma.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Removed the “rewrite” pragma; it can be replaced with standard features:
deletion and insertion. Removed the default priority pragma because it didn’t actually seem
useful.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Removed the notion of compiled grammars and the cache of compiled grammars.
</para></listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Added an option to omit headers when generating CSV output.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Added support for the “mark ambiguities” option. When enabled
<code>n:ambiguous="true"</code> attributes are added to the XML
trees.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<itemizedlist audience="coffeesacks">
<listitem>
<para>All of the NineML core components have been updated to version 3.0.0; 
CoffeeSacks incorporates the changes in
<link xlink:href="https://coffeegrinder.nineml.org/changelog.html#v300">CoffeeGrinder</link>
and
<link xlink:href="https://coffeefilter.nineml.org/changelog.html#v300">CoffeeFilter</link>
3.0.0.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>The API for resolving ambiguities has been completely refactored to align with 
CoffeeGrinder.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<itemizedlist audience="coffeepot">
<listitem>
<para>All of the NineML core components have been updated to version 3.0.0; 
CoffeePot incorporates the changes in
<link xlink:href="https://coffeegrinder.nineml.org/changelog.html#v300">CoffeeGrinder</link>,
<link xlink:href="https://coffeefilter.nineml.org/changelog.html#v300">CoffeeFilter</link>,
and
<link xlink:href="https://coffeesacks.nineml.org/changelog.html#v300">CoffeeSacks</link>,
3.0.0.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Many new command line options and configuration properties have been
added; a few have been renamed or removed.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>CoffeePot will now work with either Saxon 11 or Saxon 12.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Undefined symbols are no longer allowed, even when not in pedantic mode.
Undefined symbols are almost always an error and lead to very confusing error messages.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Added an option to analyze the grammar for ambiguity
with Anders Møller’s <link
xlink:href="https://www.brics.dk/grammar/">ambiguity analyzer</link>.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Support for compiled grammars and grammar compilation has been removed.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Fixed a number of small serialization bugs.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</revdescription>
</revision>

<revision>
<revnumber>2.2.3</revnumber>
<date>2023-06-15</date>
<revdescription>
<para audience='coffeefilter'>Fixed a typo: <methodname>setStrictAmbiguity</methodname> was setting the wrong
internal flag.</para>
    <itemizedlist audience='coffeesacks'>
    <listitem>
    <para>If a user-supplied function is called to choose an alternative, assume an
    <emphasis>unambiguous</emphasis> choice has always been made.
    Support the <literal>strictAmbiguity</literal> option to override this behavior.
    </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    <para>Support the <code>disablePragmas</code> and <code>enablePragmas</code> options
    to selectively disable or enable individual pragma types.
    </para>
    </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <itemizedlist audience='coffeepot'>
    <listitem>
    <para>Support <code>disable-pragmas</code> and <code>enable-pragmas</code> in the
    options property file and <code>--disable-pragma</code> and <code>--enable-pragma</code>
    on the command line.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    <para>Support <code>--graph-svg-option</code> on the command line to set options for
    the SVG graph output.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    <para>Improved support for reporting infinitely ambiguous
    grammars. A loop that extends through several non-terminals will
    now be detected and reported <emphasis>if</emphasis> the parse
    tree generated attempted to traverse that loop. The processor
    doesn’t enumerate every possible parse, so it may fail to detect
    loops that are on branches it does not explore.</para>
    </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
</revdescription>
</revision>
<revision>
<revnumber>2.2.2</revnumber>
<date>2023-06-15</date>
<revdescription>
<itemizedlist audience='coffeefilter'>
<listitem>
<para>Added options to enable and disable pragmas. Individual pragmas can be enabled or
disabled by name. Specify the name <code>#all</code> to enable or disable them all.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Added a <code>strictAmbiguity</code> option. If <code>strictAmbiguity</code> is true,
then a grammar will be marked ambiguous even if user-supplied priorities uniquely determined
every outcome. Added an event builder option to track whether or not any ambiguous choices
were made.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Added a warning message if a priority pragma is applied to a literal. Parsing doesn’t
distinguish between different occurrences of literals so the priority is unavailable when
resolving ambiguities.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para audience='coffeesacks'>Never released.</para>
    <para audience='coffeepot'>Fixed bug where CoffeePot had a runtime dependency on
    Saxon EE. (It can use Saxon EE, and EE is required for loading dynamic function
    libraries, but EE isn’t required for basic functionality.)</para>
</revdescription>
</revision>
<revision>
<revnumber>2.2.1</revnumber>
<date>2023-05-17</date>
<revdescription>
<para audience="coffeegrinder">Fixed a small bug in the presentation of alternative parses when
there is ambiguity. Nonterminal symbols in the alternative choices did
not necessarily have the correct attributes.</para>
<para audience='coffeefilter'/>
    <para audience='coffeesacks'>Further refined the way XML is constructed for choosing alternatives. The
    “left” and “right” sides of each alternative are now sorted so that the “left” alternative
    always matches input tokens that precede the “right” alternative. The CoffeeGrinder update
    also assures that the attributes associated with nonterminal symbols are correct.
    </para>
    <para audience='coffeepot'>Fixed bug where choices were not always presented in a
    logical order (earlier matches before later matches) when
    displaying alternatives. Updated CoffeeGrinder and fixed
    stylesheet so that marks on nonterminals are included when
    describing ambiguity.</para>
</revdescription>
</revision>
<revision>
<revnumber>2.2.0</revnumber>
<date>2023-05-06</date>
<revdescription>
<itemizedlist audience="coffeegrinder">
<listitem>
<para>CoffeeGrinder now carefully distinguishes between nonterminals
with different attributes. This introduces new nonterminals into
the grammar. These can be examined by calling
<methodname>resolveDuplicates</methodname> on the
<classname>SourceGrammar</classname>.</para>
<para>If, for example, you have two instances of a nonterminal
“B” in the grammar, where one has a mark attribute of “^” and the
other a mark attribute of “@”, after resolving duplicates there
will be two nonterminals in the grammar, “B” and “B₁”. They will
match the same inputs, but is now possible to distinguish between
them in the parse forest.</para>
<para>One particular use for this feature is the priority attribute
supported by CoffeeFilter. This attribute allows the grammar author
to associate priorities with nonterminals in ambiguous grammars to
guide the parse.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para audience="coffeegrinder">All of the infrastructure associated with “pruning” nonterminals
that lead to ε has been removed. (It hasn’t actually be used for at
least a couple of releases.)
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<itemizedlist audience='coffeefilter'>
<listitem>
<para>Leveraging changes to the CoffeeGrinder implementation, the priority
pragma now works correctly.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>References to “pruning” nonterminals has been removed (because it’s been
removed from CoffeeGrinder).
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
    <para audience='coffeesacks'>Updated the way the <link linkend="choose-alternative">choose alternative</link>
    function is called to assure that the first element in the list is always the
    current “best” choice.</para>
    <para audience='coffeepot'>Changed the <link linkend="cli">--show-grammar</link> option to display the
    grammar after duplicates have been resolved. Also changed the display to include marks.
    Documented the <literal linkend="pragma-priority">priority</literal> pragma.
    Removed the <literal>combine</literal>
    and <literal>regex</literal> pragmas from the documentation; I’m not convinced they work
    correctly.</para>
</revdescription>
</revision>
<revision>
  <revnumber>2.1.0</revnumber>
  <date>2023-04-23</date>
  <revdescription>
  <para audience="coffeegrinder">Updated the API for choosing among
  alternatives to supply the immediate context.</para>
  <para audience='coffeefilter'/>
    <para audience='coffeesacks'>Added <link linkend="choose-alternative">support</link>
    for providing a function to choose among alternative parses.</para>
    <para audience='coffeepot'>Added <link linkend="choose-alternative">support</link>
    for choosing between ambiguous parses using either an extension function or
    XPath expressions.</para>
  </revdescription>
</revision>
<revision>
  <revnumber>2.0.3</revnumber>
  <date>2023-04-15</date>
  <revdescription>
    <para audience='coffeefilter'>Corrected the encoding of the C0 and C1 control characters. Changed the encoding of
    <literal>&gt;</literal> so that it is always encoded as <literal>&amp;gt;</literal>. (This assures
    that the output will never accidentally enclude <literal>]]&gt;</literal> which marks
    the end of a CDATA section.)</para>
    <itemizedlist audience='coffeesacks'>
      <listitem>
        <para>If a UTF-8 grammar or input file begins with a byte-order-mark (BOM), the
        BOM is ignored. Set the “ignore BOM” option to
        <literal>false</literal> to disable this behavior.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Updated to use CoffeeFilter version 2.0.3 which supports ignoring the BOM
        and fixes errors in the serialization fo control characters (that’s not actually
        relevant to CoffeeSacks which doesn’t serialize the results).
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The build system has been updated to use Gradle version 8.0.2.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <itemizedlist audience='coffeepot'>
      <listitem>
        <para>Updated to use CoffeeFilter version 2.0.3 which corrects errors in
        the serialization of control characters in attributes and text content (and changes
        the serialization of <literal>&gt;</literal> to always be <literal>&amp;gt;</literal>).
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>If a UTF-8 grammar or input file begins with a byte-order-mark (BOM), the
        BOM is ignored. A new configuration property <literal>ignore-bom</literal> can be
        set to <literal>false</literal> to disable this behavior.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The build system has been updated to use Gradle version 8.0.2.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </revdescription>
</revision>
<revision>
  <revnumber>2.0.2</revnumber>
  <date>2023-04-14</date>
  <revdescription>
    <para audience='coffeefilter'>Fix encoding of characters per the
  <link xlink:href="https://www.w3.org/TR/xslt-xquery-serialization-31/#xml-output">XML Output Method</link>
  of <citetitle>XSLT and XQuery Serialization 3.1</citetitle>.</para>
  </revdescription>
</revision>
<revision>
  <revnumber>2.0.1</revnumber>
  <date>2023-04-13</date>
  <revdescription>
    <itemizedlist audience='coffeefilter'>
      <listitem>
        <para>Fixed <link xlink:href="https://github.com/nineml/coffeefilter/issues/98">#98</link>.
        Added an option to ignore the Unicode BOM on UTF-8 files. It’s
        enabled by default.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Resolved <link xlink:href="https://github.com/nineml/coffeefilter/pull/97">#97</link>.
        Improved the encoding of carriage returns in the output. If a
        carriage return in the output is not followed by a line feed,
        it will be encoded as <code>&amp;#d;</code> so that an XML
        parse of the output won’t normalize it away.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Fixed <link xlink:href="https://github.com/nineml/coffeefilter/issues/96">#96</link>.
        Improved error reporting. In the case where a parse fails with
        an unexpected character, if the character is not a visible ASCII character,
        the output includes the codepoint of the character.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Tinkered with the GitHub branch workflow so that it won’t attempt to use the SSH private
        key if it isn’t configured as a secret.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </revdescription>
</revision>
<revision>
  <revnumber>2.0.0</revnumber>
  <date>2023-04-10</date>
  <revdescription>
  <para>Making the 2.x code base the current release.</para>
  </revdescription>
</revision>
<revision>
  <revnumber>1.99.1</revnumber>
  <date>2022-06-17</date>
  <revdescription>
  <para audience="coffeegrinder">Second pre-release with GLL support;
  substantial refactoring of the internals and a new API for getting
  trees from the parse forest.
  </para>
  </revdescription>
</revision>
<revision>
  <revnumber>1.99.0</revnumber>
  <date>2022-06-08</date>
  <revdescription>
  <para audience="coffeegrinder">First pre-release that included GLL parser support. Updated to the
Invisible XML 1.0 grammar.</para>
  </revdescription>
</revision>
<revision>
  <revnumber>1.1.0</revnumber>
  <date>2022-04-16</date>
  <revdescription>
  <para audience="coffeegrinder">Internal changes to support the 15 April 2022 Invisible XML “insertions” feature, version 1.1.0</para>
    <para audience='coffeefilter'>Support for the 15 April 2022 specification, version 1.1.0</para>
    <para audience='coffeefilter'>The most significant changes are:</para>
    <orderedlist audience='coffeefilter'>
      <listitem><para>The “<symbol>repeat0</symbol>” and “<symbol>repeat1</symbol>”
      separator characters are now doubled: “<literal>item*','</literal>” becomes
      “<literal>item**','</literal>”, and “<literal>item+','</literal>” becomes
      “<literal>item++','</literal>”.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem><para>The semantics of “^” before a literal have changed. It now
      signals an insertion. The grammar fragment “<literal>'a', ^'-', 'b'</literal>”
      matches an “a” followed <emphasis>immediately</emphasis> by a “b”, but the
      XML output will be “a-b”. The text marked “^” matches nothing but is inserted
      in the output. The insertion character
      <link xlink:href="https://github.com/invisibleXML/ixml/issues/72">may change</link>.
    </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem><para>At least one whitespace character or comment is required
      between rules. (This is very unlikely to have any practical consequence
      since most grammar authors start a new rule on a new line. But where
      “<literal>a:'1'.b:'2'.</literal> used to be allowed, you must now
      write “<literal>a:'1'. b:'2'.</literal>. This avoids
      <link xlink:href="https://github.com/invisibleXML/ixml/issues/48">an ambiguity</link>
      in the grammar.)</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para audience='coffeesacks'>Support for the 15 April 2022 specification, version 1.1.0</para>
    <para audience='coffeepot'>Support for the 15 April 2022 specification, version 1.1.0</para>
    <para audience='coffeepot'>The most significant changes are:</para>
    <orderedlist audience='coffeepot'>
      <listitem><para>The “<symbol>repeat0</symbol>” and “<symbol>repeat1</symbol>”
      separator characters are now doubled: “<literal>item*','</literal>” becomes
      “<literal>item**','</literal>”, and “<literal>item+','</literal>” becomes
      “<literal>item++','</literal>”.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem><para>The semantics of “^” before a literal have changed. It now
      signals an insertion. The grammar fragment “<literal>'a', ^'-', 'b'</literal>”
      matches an “a” followed <emphasis>immediately</emphasis> by a “b”, but the
      XML output will be “a-b”. The text marked “^” matches nothing but is inserted
      in the output. The insertion character
      <link xlink:href="https://github.com/invisibleXML/ixml/issues/72">may change</link>.
    </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem><para>At least one whitespace character or comment is required
      between rules. (This is very unlikely to have any practical consequence
      since most grammar authors start a new rule on a new line. But where
      “<literal>a:'1'.b:'2'.</literal> used to be allowed, you must now
      write “<literal>a:'1'. b:'2'.</literal>. This avoids
      <link xlink:href="https://github.com/invisibleXML/ixml/issues/48">an ambiguity</link>
      in the grammar.)</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </revdescription>
</revision>
<revision>
  <revnumber>1.0.0</revnumber>
  <date>2022-03-20</date>
  <revdescription>
  <para>Initial release, version 1.0.0</para>
  </revdescription>
</revision>
</revhistory>

</appendix>
